<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE xlingpaper PUBLIC "-//XMLmind//DTD XLingPap//EN"
"XLingPap.dtd">
<xlingpaper
version="2.24.0"
><styledPaper
><lingPaper
automaticallywrapinterlinears="yes"
version="2.28.0"
><frontMatter
><title
><object
type="tDiagSap"
></object
> User Documentation</title
><author
>H. Andrew Black</author
><affiliation
>SIL International</affiliation
><emailAddress
>lingtree_support@sil.org</emailAddress
><date
>November 29, 2021</date
><version
>Version 1.1.0</version
><version
>Copyright © 2021 SIL International</version
><contents
></contents
></frontMatter
><section1
id="sIntro"
><secTitle
>Introduction</secTitle
><p
><object
type="tDiagSap"
></object
> is a tool to produce Philippine-style word tree diagrams. <object
type="tDiagSap"
></object
> is pronounced <langData
lang="lIPA"
>diɑɡsɑp</langData
><endnote
id="nPronounciation"
><p
>As opposed to <langData
lang="lIPA"
>daɪæɡsæp</langData
>.</p
></endnote
> and is short for Tagalog <langData
lang="lTagalog"
>diagramang sapin-sapin</langData
> which means "layered diagram.” You key in a description of the tree, process that description, and <object
type="tDiagSap"
></object
> shows what the tree looks like. The tree can be saved in up to two different file formats so that it can be included in papers or web pages.</p
><p
><object
type="tDiagSap"
></object
> looks like what is shown in <exampleRef
letter="xNewTree"
num="xNewTree"
></exampleRef
>.</p
><example
num="xNewTree"
><chart
><img
src="resources/NewTreeUI.png"
width="450"
></img
></chart
></example
><p
>The file name where the tree information is stored is shown in the upper left part of the window. You key the description in the top pane, process the description, and then the tree appears in the bottom pane. Since each node in the tree has binary branching, it begins with two lexical forms as shown, using “a” and “b” for the forms. You change them to be what you need. We suggest starting from the innermost forms and building the tree outward.</p
><p
>See section <sectionRef
sec="sEditDescription"
></sectionRef
> for information on keying a tree description and processing a tree.</p
><p
>You can drag the edges of the window to make it larger. You can also drag the bar between the panes to make either the tree display or the description larger (or smaller).</p
></section1
><section1
id="sEditDescription"
><secTitle
>Keying a tree description</secTitle
><p
>You key in a tree description in the top pane. To show the corresponding tree in the bottom pane, you "process" the description in any one of four ways:</p
><ul
><li
>by clicking the "process the tree description tool bar button" (<img
src="resources/DrawTree.png"
></img
>);</li
><li
>by clicking on the <object
type="tMenuItem"
>Tree</object
> menu item and then <object
type="tMenuItem"
>Draw Tree</object
>;</li
><li
>by typing <object
type="tKey"
>Ctrl-D</object
> (holding the <object
type="tKey"
>Ctrl</object
> key down while pressing the <object
type="tKey"
>D</object
> key); or</li
><li
>by using the <object
type="tMenuItem"
>Settings</object
> menu item / <object
type="tMenuItem"
>Draw tree as you type</object
> option. This will draw the tree for each keystroke you use in the tree description.<endnote
id="nInsertClosingParenthesis"
><p
>When you key an opening parenthesis, it also automatically inserts a space and a closing parenthesis. Also, when you key an opening wedge ‘&lt;’, it automatically inserts a closing wedge ‘&gt;’.</p
></endnote
> (See section <sectionRef
sec="sDrawAsType"
></sectionRef
>.)</li
></ul
><p
>All four do the same processing of the tree description and are equivalent in effect.</p
><section2
id="sBasicTreeDescription"
><secTitle
>Basic tree description</secTitle
><p
>A tree description consists of a set of nodes enclosed within parentheses. The parentheses may be nested according to the tree structure. Whenever you key a closing parenthesis ')', the matching opening parenthesis will be selected briefly. Similarly, when you key an opening parenthesis '(', any matching closing parenthesis will be selected briefly. (If you have selected the <object
type="tMenuItem"
>Settings</object
> menu item / <object
type="tMenuItem"
>Draw tree as you type</object
> option, the closing parenthesis is inserted automatically when you key an opening parenthesis.) This is to help you match nested opening and closing parentheses. You can control how long the matching parenthesis is selected; see section <sectionRef
sec="sDelayMatching"
></sectionRef
>.</p
><p
>When keying a tree description, you can force a new line to occur by pressing the <object
type="tKey"
>Enter</object
> key. You can also enter spaces and even tabs.</p
><p
>Here are three examples of how to key trees.</p
><p
>When you key what is in <exampleRef
contentType="ctRegular"
letter="xBasic1"
num="xBasic1"
></exampleRef
><exampleRef
contentType="ctKeyColor"
letter="xBasic1Color"
num="xBasic1Color"
></exampleRef
>, it shows up as in <exampleRef
letter="xBasic1Tree"
num="xBasic1Tree"
></exampleRef
>.</p
><example
contentType="ctRegular"
num="xBasic1"
><word
><langData
lang="lTreeExample"
>(((un)(lock))(able))</langData
></word
></example
><example
contentType="ctKeyColor"
num="xBasic1Color"
><word
><langData
lang="lTreeExample"
><object
type="tSynTagmeme"
>(</object
><object
type="tNonterminal"
>S</object
><object
type="tSynTagmeme"
> (</object
><object
type="tNonterminal"
>NP</object
><object
type="tSynTagmeme"
>) (</object
><object
type="tNonterminal"
>VP</object
><object
type="tSynTagmeme"
>))</object
></langData
></word
></example
><example
num="xBasic1Tree"
><chart
><img
XeLaTeXSpecial="scaled='1250'"
src="resources/unlock-able.svg"
></img
></chart
></example
><p
>And if you key what is in <exampleRef
contentType="ctRegular"
letter="xBasic2"
num="xBasic2"
></exampleRef
><exampleRef
contentType="ctKeyColor"
letter="xBasic2Color"
num="xBasic2Color"
></exampleRef
></p
><example
contentType="ctRegular"
num="xBasic2"
><word
><langData
lang="lTreeExample"
>((\1)(((p&lt;in&gt;ag) (–arál)) (an)))</langData
></word
></example
><example
contentType="ctKeyColor"
num="xBasic2Color"
><word
><langData
lang="lTreeExample"
><object
type="tSynTagmeme"
>(</object
><object
type="tNonterminal"
>S</object
><object
type="tSynTagmeme"
> (</object
><object
type="tNonterminal"
>NP</object
><object
type="tSynTagmeme"
> (</object
><object
type="tNonterminal"
>Lee</object
><object
type="tSynTagmeme"
>)) (</object
><object
type="tNonterminal"
>VP</object
><object
type="tSynTagmeme"
> (</object
><object
type="tNonterminal"
>V</object
><object
type="tSynTagmeme"
> (</object
><object
type="tNonterminal"
>gets</object
><object
type="tSynTagmeme"
>)) (</object
><object
type="tNonterminal"
>NP</object
><object
type="tSynTagmeme"
> (</object
><object
type="tNonterminal"
>Det</object
><object
type="tSynTagmeme"
> (</object
><object
type="tNonterminal"
>the</object
><object
type="tSynTagmeme"
>)) (</object
><object
type="tNonterminal"
>N</object
><object
type="tSynTagmeme"
> (</object
><object
type="tNonterminal"
>idea</object
><object
type="tSynTagmeme"
>)))))</object
></langData
></word
></example
><pc
>it will produce what is in <exampleRef
letter="xBasic2Tree"
num="xBasic2Tree"
></exampleRef
></pc
><example
num="xBasic2Tree"
><chart
><img
XeLaTeXSpecial="scaled='1250'"
src="resources/pinagaralan.svg"
></img
></chart
></example
><p
>In example <exampleRef
letter="xBasic2"
num="xBasic2"
></exampleRef
>, notice that the infix material is indicated by typing an opening wedge ‘&lt;’, the infix form, and then a closing wedge ‘&gt;.’ The node level of the infix is indicated by the <langData
lang="lTreeExample"
>(\1)</langData
> portion which we call an infix index. We use a backslash followed by a 1 (one) to indicate the first infix in the tree (from left-to-right); <langData
lang="lTreeExample"
>(\2)</langData
> to indicate the second infix, etc.<endnote
id="nNineInfixIndexes"
><p
>A maximum of nine infixes are allowed.</p
></endnote
> The backslash is used to avoid the ambiguity that occurs when a font uses the same glyph for both the digit 1 and a lower case l.</p
><p
>The description in example <exampleRef
letter="xTwoInfixes"
num="xTwoInfixes"
></exampleRef
> has two infixes in it and produces what is given in example <exampleRef
letter="xTwoInfixesTree"
num="xTwoInfixesTree"
></exampleRef
>.</p
><example
num="xTwoInfixes"
><word
><langData
lang="lTreeExample"
>((\1) ((g&lt;in&gt;) ((pí-)((\2) ((p&lt;in&gt;a-)((m-)(ulod)))))))</langData
></word
></example
><example
num="xTwoInfixesTree"
><chart
><img
XeLaTeXSpecial="scaled='1250'"
src="resources/ginpipinamulod.svg"
></img
></chart
></example
><p
>You may set font and color information for the lexical items. See section <sectionRef
sec="sFontColor"
></sectionRef
>. When you do, the font and color will show in the description pane as well as in the drawn tree.</p
></section2
><section2
id="sParentheses"
><secTitle
>Handling parentheses</secTitle
><p
>If you need to put an opening or closing parenthesis in your tree, quote the parenthesis by using a backslash immediately before it. Similarly, if you need to put an opening or closing wedge in your tree, quote the wedge by using a backslash immediately before it.</p
></section2
></section1
><section1
id="sFormatting"
><secTitle
>Formating a tree</secTitle
><p
>You can adjust the positioning of the tree and its nodes as well as choose the fonts, sizes, and colors for the lexical forms. You can also set a background color and determine the color and thickness of the lines in the trees.</p
><p
>All of these parameters are available on the <object
type="tMenuItem"
>Format</object
> menu item.</p
><p
>Please note that these settings are associated with each individual tree diagram. Thus, you can set them to make a given tree diagram look its best.</p
><section2
id="sUseDashedLines"
><secTitle
>Use dashed lines for split infixed base</secTitle
><p
>The first item under the main <object
type="tMenuItem"
>Format</object
> menu item is <object
type="tMenuItem"
>Use dashed lines for split infixed base</object
>. When this has a check mark before it, the horizontal and vertical lines connecting the infixed base's before and after portions will be drawn using dashed lines. For example, the description in example <exampleRef
letter="xDashedLines"
num="xDashedLines"
></exampleRef
> will appear as in example <exampleRef
letter="xDashedLinesTree"
num="xDashedLinesTree"
></exampleRef
>.</p
><example
num="xDashedLines"
><word
><langData
lang="lTreeExample"
>((\1)((p&lt;in&gt;a-)((m-)(ulod))))</langData
></word
></example
><example
num="xDashedLinesTree"
><chart
><img
XeLaTeXSpecial="scaled='1050'"
src="resources/DashedLines.svg"
></img
></chart
></example
></section2
><section2
id="sRigtToLeft"
><secTitle
>Draw a tree right-to-left</secTitle
><p
>The second item under the main <object
type="tMenuItem"
>Format</object
> menu item is <object
type="tMenuItem"
>Draw tree right-to-left</object
>. When this has a check mark before it, the tree will be drawn from right-to-left. (This is not currently implemented.) <comment
>For example, if the non-terminal, lexical, and gloss fonts and colors have been set as shown in example <exampleRef
letter="xHebrewRTLTree"
num="xHebrewRTLTree"
></exampleRef
> below, then the description given in <exampleRef
letter="xHebrewRTL"
num="xHebrewRTL"
></exampleRef
> looks like example <exampleRef
letter="xHebrewRTLTree"
num="xHebrewRTLTree"
></exampleRef
> when the <object
type="tMenuItem"
>Draw tree right-to-left</object
> is checked.</comment
></p
><example
contentType="ctKeyColor"
num="xHebrewRTL"
><word
><langData
lang="lTreeExample"
>(S (PP (\T\L <langData
lang="lHebrew"
>בְּרֵאשִׁית</langData
> (\G in the beginning ) ) ) (VP (V (\L <langData
lang="lHebrew"
>בָּרָא</langData
>(\G created )) ) (NP (N(\L <langData
lang="lHebrew"
>אֱלֹהִים</langData
> (\G God )) ) ) (NP (NP (DObj (\L <langData
lang="lHebrew"
>אֵת</langData
> (\G obj )) ) (N (\L <langData
lang="lHebrew"
>הַשָּׁמַיִם</langData
> (\G the heavens ))) ) (NP (DObj (\L <langData
lang="lHebrew"
>וְאֵת</langData
> (\G and.obj )) ) (N (\L <langData
lang="lHebrew"
>הָאָרֶץ</langData
> (\G the earth ) ) )) ) ))</langData
></word
></example
><example
contentType="ctKeyColor"
num="xHebrewRTLTree"
><chart
><img
XeLaTeXSpecial="scaled='1050'"
src="resources/Hebrew.svg"
></img
></chart
></example
><pc
contentType="ctKeyColor"
>The output looks like example <exampleRef
letter="xHebrewLTRTree"
num="xHebrewLTRTree"
></exampleRef
> when the <object
type="tMenuItem"
>Draw tree right-to-left</object
> is left unchecked.</pc
><example
contentType="ctKeyColor"
num="xHebrewLTRTree"
><chart
><img
XeLaTeXSpecial="scaled='1050'"
src="resources/HebrewLTR.svg"
></img
></chart
></example
></section2
><section2
id="sFontColor"
><secTitle
>Setting the font and color information</secTitle
><p
>The next portion of the main <object
type="tMenuItem"
>Format</object
> menu item is for setting font and color information for the lexical material.</p
><p
>When you select this menu item, it brings up a dialog box showing font family, style, size and color options. The set of style options shown depends on what styles the selected font has. So if the font only has “Regular,” then only Regular will appear in the list of styles.</p
><p
>If you click in the Font list, then you can key a letter and it will go to the first font name that begins with that letter.</p
><p
>To get the color chooser, click on the drop-down box in the lower left portion of the dialog. It will look something like what is in <exampleRef
letter="xColorChooser"
num="xColorChooser"
></exampleRef
>.</p
><example
num="xColorChooser"
><chart
><img
src="resources/ColorChooser.png"
></img
></chart
></example
><pc
>You can click on the color you want or you can click on the “Custom Color” link. Doing so gives you what is in <exampleRef
letter="xCustomColor"
num="xCustomColor"
></exampleRef
>.</pc
><example
num="xCustomColor"
><chart
><img
src="resources/CustomColor.png"
></img
></chart
></example
><p
>If you click on the Web tab, you can key in a code for the color. A list of color names, their color, and the code can be found at <link
href="https://www.w3schools.com/cssref/css_colors.asp"
>https://​www.w3schools.com/​cssref/​css_colors.asp</link
>.</p
><p
>When you click on the main dialog's OK button, the tree description and tree diagram will reflect the new font and color information.</p
></section2
><section2
id="sTreeSpacing"
><secTitle
>Tree spacing parameters</secTitle
><p
>The fourth item in the main <object
type="tMenuItem"
>Format</object
> menu item is <object
type="tMenuItem"
>Tree spacing parameters</object
>. When you select this menu item, it brings up a dialog that looks like what is in <exampleRef
letter="xTreeSpacingParameters"
num="xTreeSpacingParameters"
></exampleRef
>.</p
><example
num="xTreeSpacingParameters"
><chart
><img
src="resources/TreeSpacingParameters.png"
width="450"
></img
></chart
></example
><pc
>Each row has a description of the parameter and a box to key a numerical value. You can use negative numbers, if necessary.</pc
></section2
><section2
id="sBackgroundLine"
><secTitle
>Background and line parameters</secTitle
><p
>The second from last item in the main <object
type="tMenuItem"
>Format</object
> menu item is <object
type="tMenuItem"
>Tree spacing parameters</object
>. When you select this menu item, it brings up a dialog that looks like what is in <exampleRef
letter="xBackgroundLine"
num="xBackgroundLine"
></exampleRef
>.</p
><example
num="xBackgroundLine"
><chart
><img
src="resources/BackgroundLine.png"
width="450"
></img
></chart
></example
><pc
>You can set the color of the tree background and the width and color of the lines.</pc
></section2
><section2
id="sSaveForNew"
><secTitle
>Saving format information for use with new tree diagrams</secTitle
><p
>The last item in the main <object
type="tMenuItem"
>Format</object
> menu item is <object
type="tMenuItem"
>Save the current tree parameters to use for new tree diagrams</object
>. When you select this menu item, the set of tree formatting values used for the current tree are remembered for any new tree diagrams in the future.</p
></section2
></section1
><section1
id="sSettings"
><secTitle
>User convenience options</secTitle
><p
>The <object
type="tMenuItem"
>Settings</object
> menu item has several options you can use to (hopefully) improve your experience with using <object
type="tDiagSap"
></object
>. These are described below along with one useful item under the <object
type="tMenuItem"
>Help</object
> menu.</p
><p
>Please note that these settings are associated with the <object
type="tDiagSap"
></object
> program on your computer. Once you set them, they will be used each time you use <object
type="tDiagSap"
></object
> (until you change them, of course).</p
><section2
id="sSyntagmemeFontSize"
><secTitle
>Font size for tree description symbols</secTitle
><p
>The first item under the main <object
type="tMenuItem"
>Settings</object
> menu item is <object
type="tMenuItem"
>Font size for tree description symbols</object
>. This lets you set the font size for the symbols used in a tree description, that is <object
type="tSynTagmeme"
>(</object
>, <object
type="tSynTagmeme"
>)</object
>, <object
type="tSynTagmeme"
>&lt;</object
>, <object
type="tSynTagmeme"
>&gt;</object
>, <object
type="tSynTagmeme"
>\1</object
>, <object
type="tSynTagmeme"
>\2</object
>, etc. The motivation for this is that some very high resolution screens may make it a bit difficult to see these or, alternatively, they may appear quite large in comparison to the other material in a tree description. So you can change their size.</p
></section2
><section2
id="sDrawAsType"
><secTitle
>Draw the tree as you type</secTitle
><p
>The second item under the main <object
type="tMenuItem"
>Settings</object
> menu item is <object
type="tMenuItem"
>Draw tree as you type</object
>. When this menu item has a check mark before it, each time you change or edit something in the tree description, <object
type="tDiagSap"
></object
> will redraw the tree diagram.</p
><p
>When using this mode, whenever you key an opening parenthesis, <object
type="tDiagSap"
></object
> will automatically insert a space, an “a” and a closing parenthesis. The idea is to help you keep opening and closing parentheses matched. It will also automatically insert a closing wedge whenever you key an opening wedge.</p
><p
>Furthermore, if you key an opening parenthesis after the initial opening parenthesis or before the final parenthesis, <object
type="tDiagSap"
></object
> will also insert additional parentheses to keep the tree in its correct shape. This is to help you build the tree one level at a time. For example, suppose you are creating a tree for one possible reading of the word “unlockable.” You begin with a new tree and change the “a” and “b” to “lock” and “able,“ respectively. It will look like what is shown in example <exampleRef
letter="xLockable"
num="xLockable"
></exampleRef
>.</p
><example
num="xLockable"
><chart
><img
src="resources/lockable.png"
></img
></chart
></example
><pc
>If you then place the cursor after the initial opening parenthesis and type an opening parenthesis, it will look like what is in example <exampleRef
letter="xA-lockable"
num="xA-lockable"
></exampleRef
>.</pc
><example
num="xA-lockable"
><chart
><img
src="resources/un-lockableUI.png"
></img
></chart
></example
><pc
>You would replace the “a” with “un.”</pc
><p
>Alternatively, you could begin with a new tree and change the “a” and “b” to “un” and “lock,” respectively, so it would look like example <exampleRef
letter="xUnlock"
num="xUnlock"
></exampleRef
>.</p
><example
num="xUnlock"
><chart
><img
src="resources/unlock.png"
></img
></chart
></example
><pc
>If you then place the cursor just before the final opening parenthesis and type an opening parenthesis, it will look like what is in example <exampleRef
letter="xUnlock-ableUI"
num="xUnlock-ableUI"
></exampleRef
>.</pc
><example
num="xUnlock-ableUI"
><chart
><img
src="resources/unlock-ableUI.png"
></img
></chart
></example
><pc
>You would replace the “a” with “able.”</pc
><p
>Sometimes the automatic drawing of the tree diagram will cause an error message to appear where the tree diagram normally shows; for example, if you have deleted a parenthesis and no longer have a matching opening or closing one, then there will be a message about a missing opening or closing parenthesis. As soon as the tree description is well-formed, the tree diagram will appear.</p
></section2
><section2
id="sArrowKeysShowMatching"
><secTitle
>Show matching parenthesis with arrow keys</secTitle
><p
>As mentioned in section <sectionRef
sec="sBasicTreeDescription"
></sectionRef
>, when you key a parenthesis, <object
type="tDiagSap"
></object
> will temporarily select the matching parenthesis to help you see the nested structure of the description. There are times, however, when you need to see matching parentheses and it would be nice if you did not have to delete a parenthesis and immediately re-key it. For this reason, there is the third item under the main <object
type="tMenuItem"
>Settings</object
> menu item: <object
type="tMenuItem"
>Show matching parenthesis with arrow keys</object
>. When this is checked, whenever you use an arrow key to cross over a parenthesis in the description, <object
type="tDiagSap"
></object
> will temporarily select the parenthesis that matches the one crossed over.</p
><p
>Besides using this menu option, you can also use the toolbar button shown in <exampleRef
letter="xShowMatchingParensArrows"
num="xShowMatchingParensArrows"
></exampleRef
>.</p
><example
num="xShowMatchingParensArrows"
><table
border="1"
><tr
><th
align="center"
>Show matching with arrows</th
><th
align="center"
>Do not show matching with arrows</th
></tr
><tr
><td
XeLaTeXSpecial="valign-fixup='-3pt'"
align="center"
><img
src="resources/ShowParensPressed.png"
></img
></td
><td
XeLaTeXSpecial="valign-fixup='-3pt'"
align="center"
><img
src="resources/ShowParensNotPressed.png"
></img
></td
></tr
></table
></example
></section2
><section2
id="sDelayMatching"
><secTitle
>Delay to use when showing matching parentheses</secTitle
><p
>The fourth item under the main <object
type="tMenuItem"
>Settings</object
> menu item is <object
type="tMenuItem"
>Delay to use when showing matching parentheses</object
>. The default delay is 750 milliseconds (i.e., three quarters of a second). Depending on your typing speed, you may want to change this value. Use this menu item to change the delay value to be shorter or longer. The shortest allowed value is 125 milliseconds (i.e., one eighth of a second) and the longest value allowed is 4000 milliseconds (i.e., 4 seconds).</p
></section2
><section2
id="sInterfaceLanguage"
><secTitle
>Change the interface language</secTitle
><p
>You can set the user interface language by using the <object
type="tMenuItem"
>Settings / Change the interface language</object
> menu item. This brings up a dialog box showing the current interface language in a drop down chooser. Click on the chooser's drop down button to see other interface language choices. The choices given use the name of the language in the current interface language (so if the current interface language is English, then it will show “Spanish” as an option; if the current interface language is Spanish, it will show English as “inglés”).</p
><p
>The current version has English, some French and a rough, most likely often inaccurate version of Spanish. Any corrections to the Spanish or French are welcome.</p
></section2
><section2
id="sQuicReferenceGuide"
><secTitle
>Quick Reference Guide</secTitle
><p
>The main <object
type="tMenuItem"
>Help</object
> menu item has a <object
type="tMenuItem"
>Quick Reference Guide</object
> item. When you select this item, it brings up a dialog box containing a list of the special symbols you can key to get a particular result. You can position and/or resize this dialog so that you can see it while also keying a tree description. That is, unlike most dialog boxes, you do not have to close this dialog box before you can continue working. It will stay open until you close it.</p
></section2
></section1
><section1
id="sOutput"
><secTitle
>Saving the tree</secTitle
><p
>While the resulting tree looks nice within the <object
type="tDiagSap"
></object
> program, what one usually wants to do is to embed the tree diagram in some other document. <object
type="tDiagSap"
></object
> allows you to save the tree in up to two formats:</p
><ul
><li
>A Portable Network Graphics (*.png) file.</li
><li
>Scalable Vector Graphics format (*.svg) file.</li
></ul
><p
>You select which of these formats you wish to save by clicking on the <object
type="tMenuItem"
>File</object
> menu item and then clicking on the <object
type="tMenuItem"
>Save tree as .png</object
> and/or <object
type="tMenuItem"
>Save tree as .svg</object
> items.</p
><p
>Besides using these menu options, you can also use the toolbar buttons shown in <exampleRef
letter="xSaveAsPNG"
num="xSaveAsPNG"
></exampleRef
> and <exampleRef
letter="xSaveAsSVG"
num="xSaveAsSVG"
></exampleRef
>.</p
><example
num="xSaveAsPNG"
><table
border="1"
><tr
><th
align="center"
>Save tree as .png</th
><th
align="center"
>Do not save tree as .png</th
></tr
><tr
><td
XeLaTeXSpecial="valign-fixup='-3pt'"
align="center"
><img
src="resources/PngPressed.png"
></img
></td
><td
XeLaTeXSpecial="valign-fixup='-3pt'"
align="center"
><img
src="resources/PngNotPressed.png"
></img
></td
></tr
></table
></example
><example
num="xSaveAsSVG"
><table
border="1"
><tr
><th
align="center"
>Save tree as .svg</th
><th
align="center"
>Do not save tree as .svg</th
></tr
><tr
><td
XeLaTeXSpecial="valign-fixup='-3pt'"
align="center"
><img
src="resources/SvgPressed.png"
></img
></td
><td
XeLaTeXSpecial="valign-fixup='-3pt'"
align="center"
><img
src="resources/SvgNotPressed.png"
></img
></td
></tr
></table
></example
><p
>You merely check the formats you wish to use. <object
type="tDiagSap"
></object
> will produce a file with the given extension for each checked format. The file name (i.e., the part before the extension) is the same for all of them.</p
><p
>In addition, you will find a file with an extension of ".diagsap" which contains information for <object
type="tDiagSap"
></object
> to draw the tree. Do not edit this file. This has all the information about the tree description that <object
type="tDiagSap"
></object
> uses.</p
><p
>Note that once you set these Save Formats, they stay in effect for all ensuing trees you build.</p
><p
>Of these two formats, we highly recommend that you use the Scalable Vector Graphics format (*.svg) whenever possible. This is because SVG format will always look nice in a web browser or a PDF file, no matter how large the user makes the page appear.</p
><p
>Another reason for using the SVG format is that if you find that <object
type="tDiagSap"
></object
> cannot do everything you need for a particular tree diagram, you can produce the SVG form and then use a tool like <object
type="tTool"
>InkScape</object
> to do the rest. See <link
href="https://inkscape.org/en/"
>https://​inkscape.org/​en/</link
> for more on <object
type="tTool"
>InkScape</object
>.</p
><p
>If you do find yourself in a situation where you absolutely must have a pure graphics image file and the Portable Network Graphics (*.png) form is not acceptable, you can use various tools to convert your PNG file to some other graphics image format. Example <exampleRef
letter="xGraphicImageConverters"
num="xGraphicImageConverters"
></exampleRef
> lists some possibilities.</p
><example
num="xGraphicImageConverters"
><table
border="1"
><tr
><th
>Operating System</th
><th
>Tool</th
><th
>Potential formats</th
></tr
><tr
><th
>Windows</th
><td
><object
type="tTool"
>Paint</object
></td
><td
>.bmp, .jpg, .gif, .tif</td
></tr
><tr
><th
>Mac OS X</th
><td
><object
type="tTool"
>Preview</object
></td
><td
>.jpeg, .tiff</td
></tr
><tr
><th
>Linux</th
><td
><object
type="tTool"
>Image Viewer</object
></td
><td
>.bmp, .jpeg, .gif, .tiff</td
></tr
></table
></example
><p
>In addition, there is the <object
type="tTool"
>XnConvert</object
> program available at <link
href="https://www.xnview.com/en/xnconvert/"
>https://​www.xnview.com/​en/​xnconvert/</link
>. It runs on all three operating systems and can convert to many different image formats.</p
></section1
><section1
id="sErrorMessage"
><secTitle
>Error messages</secTitle
><p
>Whenever you process a tree description, if <object
type="tDiagSap"
></object
> notices any error in the description, it will show the error message in the same place where the tree diagram usually appears. The message tries to indicate what the problem is and where it was found (in terms of line number and character position). It also shows where in the tree description the error was found. While these messages are intended to be helpful, sometimes it may be the case that what needs to be done to fix the error is not necessarily what the message implies will fix it.</p
><p
>For example, when the message is about a missing closing parenthesis, the message actually indicates the innermost place where the outer parentheses match. So it may not be the best place to insert a closing parenthesis; but, on the other hand, it may work just fine. You may want to use the arrow keys to find the best place to fix the problem (see section <sectionRef
sec="sArrowKeysShowMatching"
></sectionRef
>).</p
><p
>Another thing to note is that for longer, more complicated tree descriptions, it may take a 2-3 times longer for the tree drawing process to happen if it finds an error.</p
><p
>Example <exampleRef
letter="xErrorTypes"
num="xErrorTypes"
></exampleRef
> lists the error types <object
type="tDiagSap"
></object
> reports along with a brief description of what the error type might mean.</p
><example
num="xErrorTypes"
><table
border="1"
><tr
><th
width="2in"
>Error Type</th
><th
width="3.25in"
>Meaning</th
></tr
><tr
><td
><object
type="tErrorType"
>Missing closing parenthesis</object
></td
><td
>At least one closing parenthesis is missing.</td
></tr
><tr
><td
><object
type="tErrorType"
>Missing closing wedge</object
></td
><td
>A closing wedge is missing.</td
></tr
><tr
><td
><object
type="tErrorType"
>Missing constituent</object
></td
><td
>There is a node but it does not have both a left and a right portion; it needs another portion (enclosed within parentheses).</td
></tr
><tr
><td
><object
type="tErrorType"
>Missing constituent on the right</object
></td
><td
>There is a node that has a left portion, but not a right portion; it needs a right portion (enclosed within parentheses).</td
></tr
><tr
><td
><object
type="tErrorType"
>Missing content</object
></td
><td
>Some lexical material was expected but not found.</td
></tr
><tr
><td
><object
type="tErrorType"
>Missing content and closing parenthesis</object
></td
><td
>Some lexical material was expected but not found. In addition, there should be a closing parenthesis after that content.</td
></tr
><tr
><td
><object
type="tErrorType"
>Missing opening parenthesis</object
></td
><td
>An opening parenthesis needs to be inserted.</td
></tr
><tr
><td
><object
type="tErrorType"
>Missing opening wedges</object
></td
><td
>An opening wedge needs to be inserted.</td
></tr
><tr
><td
><object
type="tErrorType"
>Syntax error in description</object
></td
><td
>Perhaps obviously, this indicates some kind of error, but <object
type="tDiagSap"
></object
> failed to identify it. Look at where it was found and see if you can guess what might be wrong.</td
></tr
><tr
><td
><object
type="tErrorType"
>The infix "xyz" has no matching index.</object
></td
><td
>The infix (indicated by what is inside the quotes) does not have a corresponding infix index (which is indicated by <langData
lang="lTreeExample"
>(\1)</langData
>, <langData
lang="lTreeExample"
>(\2)</langData
>, etc.)</td
></tr
><tr
><td
><object
type="tErrorType"
>The infix index "xyz" appears more than once. It must only be there one time.</object
></td
><td
>The same infix index occurs more than once. E.g., there are two instances of <langData
lang="lTreeExample"
>(\1)</langData
>.</td
></tr
><tr
><td
><object
type="tErrorType"
>The infix index "xyz" has no matching infix. This is not allowed; change its number or add an infix base.</object
></td
><td
>An infix index was found that does not have a corresponding infix.</td
></tr
><tr
><td
><object
type="tErrorType"
>There is content after a completed tree</object
></td
><td
>A “completed tree” means that there is a matching closing parenthesis for the first opening parenthesis. This error indicates that some content or nodes occur after the closing parenthesis which matches the first opening parenthesis. It may be that you need another opening parenthesis before the first opening parenthesis or maybe some content was keyed in the wrong place at the end.</td
></tr
><tr
><td
><object
type="tErrorType"
>Too many closing parentheses</object
></td
><td
>A closing parenthesis was found that does not have a matching opening parenthesis.</td
></tr
><tr
><td
><object
type="tErrorType"
>Two consecutive nodes found between "xyz" and "abc". This is not allowed; change one to lexical material, an infix index, or an infix base.</object
></td
><td
>Since every node is binary, one part must be lexical material, an infix, or an infix index and the other part must be the same or a node. <object
type="tDiagSap"
></object
> found that there were two nodes one after the other.</td
></tr
></table
></example
></section1
><section1
id="sKnownProblems"
><secTitle
>Known problems</secTitle
><p
>The following items are known to be less than desirable with this version of <object
type="tDiagSap"
></object
>:</p
><ul
><li
>The splitter bar between the description and the drawing may change between invocations of <object
type="tDiagSap"
></object
>. We hope to fix this.</li
><li
>When showing matching parentheses while using arrow keys (see section <sectionRef
sec="sArrowKeysShowMatching"
></sectionRef
>), if you type several arrow keys quickly, the cursor caret may not be where you expect it. Either<ul
><li
>turn off the show matching parentheses with the arrow keys option;</li
><li
>set the delay to be shorter (see section <sectionRef
sec="sDelayMatching"
></sectionRef
>); or</li
><li
>wait for the matching parenthesis to show before pressing the next arrow key.</li
></ul
></li
><li
>The ability to produce a right-to-left tree diagram is not yet implemented.</li
><li
>If you have an infix and delete the opening wedge and then do an Undo operation, <object
type="tDiagSap"
></object
> will crash and you will see an error dialog box asking you to copy the message and email it to <link
href="mailto:lingtree_support_lsdev@sil.org"
>lingtree_support_lsdev@sil.org</link
>. Obviously, we know about this one but have yet to fix it. You do not need to email it to us. We will try and fix it in a later version. If you do not use Undo, but instead re-type the opening wedge, there is no such crash.</li
></ul
></section1
><section1
id="sSupport"
><secTitle
>Support</secTitle
><p
>If you have any questions with <object
type="tDiagSap"
></object
> or find bugs in it, please send an email to <link
href="mailto:lingtree_support@sil.org"
>lingtree_support@sil.org</link
> or go to the <object
type="tDiagSap"
></object
> web site at <link
href="https://software.sil.org/lingtree/"
>https://​software.sil.org/​lingtree/</link
>.</p
></section1
><backMatter
><endnotes
></endnotes
><references
></references
></backMatter
><languages
><language
id="lVernacular"
name="vernacular"
></language
><language
id="lGloss"
name="gloss"
></language
><language
id="en"
></language
><language
font-family="Ezra SIL"
id="lHebrew"
></language
><language
color="black"
font-family="Courier New"
id="lTreeExample"
></language
><language
color="blue"
font-family="Charis SIL"
id="lIPA"
></language
><language
color="purple"
font-family="Charis SIL"
id="lTagalog"
></language
></languages
><types
><comment
>The following types are provided as pre-set examples. You may well want to create your own types that refer to one or more of these. You do that by typing in the names of the types in the types attribute of your type.</comment
><type
font-weight="bold"
id="tBold"
></type
><type
font-style="italic"
font-weight="bold"
id="tBoldItalic"
></type
><type
font-weight="bold"
id="tEmphasis"
></type
><type
id="tGrammaticalGloss"
types="tSmallCaps"
></type
><type
font-style="italic"
id="tItalic"
></type
><type
cssSpecial="text-decoration:none"
id="tNoOverline"
xsl-foSpecial="text-decoration=&quot;no-overline&quot;"
></type
><type
font-variant="normal"
id="tNoSmallCaps"
></type
><type
cssSpecial="text-decoration:none"
id="tNoStrikethrough"
xsl-foSpecial="text-decoration=&quot;no-line-through&quot;"
></type
><type
cssSpecial="text-decoration:none"
id="tNoUnderline"
xsl-foSpecial="text-decoration=&quot;no-underline&quot;"
></type
><type
cssSpecial="text-decoration:overline"
id="tOverline"
xsl-foSpecial="text-decoration=&quot;overline&quot;"
></type
><type
font-style="normal"
font-variant="normal"
font-weight="normal"
id="tRegular"
></type
><type
font-family="Charis SIL Small Caps"
id="tSmallCaps"
></type
><type
XeLaTeXSpecial="line-through"
cssSpecial="text-decoration:line-through"
id="tStrikethrough"
xsl-foSpecial="text-decoration=&quot;line-through&quot;"
></type
><type
XeLaTeXSpecial="subscript"
cssSpecial="vertical-align:sub;"
font-size="65%"
id="tSubscript"
xsl-foSpecial="baseline-shift='sub'"
></type
><type
XeLaTeXSpecial="superscript"
cssSpecial="vertical-align:super;"
font-size="65%"
id="tSuperscript"
xsl-foSpecial="baseline-shift='super'"
></type
><type
XeLaTeXSpecial="underline"
cssSpecial="text-decoration:underline"
id="tUnderline"
xsl-foSpecial="text-decoration=&quot;underline&quot;"
></type
><comment
>Add your custom types here.</comment
><type
before="DiagSap"
color="navy"
id="tDiagSap"
></type
><type
id="tDialogTitle"
></type
><type
color="#800080"
font-family="Arial"
font-size="12pt"
font-style="italic"
id="tEmpty"
></type
><type
color="red"
id="tErrorType"
></type
><type
color="blue"
font-family="Arial"
id="tGloss"
></type
><type
color="#009900"
font-family="Charis SIL"
font-weight="bold"
id="tKey"
></type
><type
color="red"
font-family="Arial"
font-size="12pt"
id="tLexical"
></type
><type
color="maroon"
id="tMenuItem"
></type
><type
color="black"
font-family="Arial"
font-size="12pt"
id="tNonterminal"
></type
><type
color="black"
font-family="Monospaced"
font-weight="bold"
id="tSynTagmeme"
></type
><type
color="navy"
id="tTool"
></type
></types
><contentControl
><contentTypes
><contentType
id="ctKeyColor"
>Tree description in color/font</contentType
><contentType
id="ctRegular"
>Tree description plain</contentType
></contentTypes
><contentControlChoices
><contentControlChoice
active="yes"
exclude="ctKeyColor"
>Tree description regular</contentControlChoice
><contentControlChoice
active="no"
>Tree description color/font</contentControlChoice
></contentControlChoices
></contentControl
></lingPaper
><publisherStyleSheet
><publisherStyleSheetName
>SIL International Paper Stylesheet</publisherStyleSheetName
><publisherStyleSheetVersion
>0.4.5</publisherStyleSheetVersion
><pageLayout
><pageWidth
>8.5in</pageWidth
><pageHeight
>11in</pageHeight
><pageTopMargin
>.7in</pageTopMargin
><pageBottomMargin
>.675in</pageBottomMargin
><pageInsideMargin
>1.5in</pageInsideMargin
><pageOutsideMargin
>1in</pageOutsideMargin
><useThesisSubmissionStyle
></useThesisSubmissionStyle
><headerMargin
>.25in</headerMargin
><footerMargin
>.25in</footerMargin
><paragraphIndent
>1em</paragraphIndent
><blockQuoteIndent
>.125in</blockQuoteIndent
><lineSpacing
></lineSpacing
><defaultFontFamily
>Charis SIL</defaultFontFamily
><basicPointSize
>12</basicPointSize
><footnotePointSize
>10</footnotePointSize
><footnoteLine
leaderlength="2in"
leaderpattern="rule"
textalign="left"
></footnoteLine
><linkLayout
color="blue"
decoration="underline"
><abbrRefLinkLayout
></abbrRefLinkLayout
><appendixRefLinkLayout
></appendixRefLinkLayout
><citationLinkLayout
></citationLinkLayout
><contentsLinkLayout
></contentsLinkLayout
><endnoteRefLinkLayout
></endnoteRefLinkLayout
><exampleRefLinkLayout
></exampleRefLinkLayout
><genericRefLinkLayout
></genericRefLinkLayout
><indexLinkLayout
></indexLinkLayout
><interlinearRefLinkLayout
></interlinearRefLinkLayout
><linkLinkLayout
></linkLinkLayout
><sectionRefLinkLayout
></sectionRefLinkLayout
><urlLinkLayout
></urlLinkLayout
></linkLayout
><headerFooterPageStyles
font-family="Times New Roman"
font-size="9pt"
font-style="italic"
><headerFooterFirstPage
><header
><leftHeaderFooterItem
><nothing
></nothing
></leftHeaderFooterItem
><centerHeaderFooterItem
><nothing
></nothing
></centerHeaderFooterItem
><rightHeaderFooterItem
><nothing
></nothing
></rightHeaderFooterItem
></header
><footer
><leftHeaderFooterItem
><nothing
></nothing
></leftHeaderFooterItem
><centerHeaderFooterItem
><pageNumber
font-size="smaller"
font-style="italic"
></pageNumber
></centerHeaderFooterItem
><rightHeaderFooterItem
><nothing
></nothing
></rightHeaderFooterItem
></footer
></headerFooterFirstPage
><headerFooterOddEvenPages
><headerFooterEvenPage
><header
><leftHeaderFooterItem
><pageNumber
font-size="smaller"
font-style="italic"
></pageNumber
></leftHeaderFooterItem
><centerHeaderFooterItem
><nothing
></nothing
></centerHeaderFooterItem
><rightHeaderFooterItem
><paperTitle
font-size="smaller"
font-style="italic"
></paperTitle
></rightHeaderFooterItem
></header
><footer
><leftHeaderFooterItem
><nothing
></nothing
></leftHeaderFooterItem
><centerHeaderFooterItem
><nothing
></nothing
></centerHeaderFooterItem
><rightHeaderFooterItem
><nothing
></nothing
></rightHeaderFooterItem
></footer
></headerFooterEvenPage
><headerFooterOddPage
><header
><leftHeaderFooterItem
><sectionTitle
font-size="smaller"
font-style="italic"
></sectionTitle
></leftHeaderFooterItem
><centerHeaderFooterItem
><nothing
></nothing
></centerHeaderFooterItem
><rightHeaderFooterItem
><pageNumber
font-size="smaller"
font-style="italic"
></pageNumber
></rightHeaderFooterItem
></header
><footer
><leftHeaderFooterItem
><nothing
></nothing
></leftHeaderFooterItem
><centerHeaderFooterItem
><nothing
></nothing
></centerHeaderFooterItem
><rightHeaderFooterItem
><nothing
></nothing
></rightHeaderFooterItem
></footer
></headerFooterOddPage
></headerFooterOddEvenPages
></headerFooterPageStyles
></pageLayout
><frontMatterLayout
><comment
>Front Matter Layout</comment
><titleLayout
font-size="18pt"
font-weight="bold"
pagebreakbefore="yes"
spacebefore="1.25in"
startonoddpage="yes"
textalign="center"
></titleLayout
><subtitleLayout
font-size="14pt"
font-weight="bold"
textalign="center"
></subtitleLayout
><authorLayout
font-style="italic"
textalign="center"
></authorLayout
><affiliationLayout
font-style="italic"
textalign="center"
></affiliationLayout
><emailAddressLayout
font-size="90%"
textalign="center"
></emailAddressLayout
><presentedAtLayout
font-size="10pt"
textalign="center"
textbefore="Presented at "
></presentedAtLayout
><dateLayout
font-size="10pt"
textalign="center"
></dateLayout
><versionLayout
font-size="10pt"
textalign="center"
></versionLayout
><contentsLayout
font-size="14pt"
font-weight="bold"
spaceafter="12pt"
spacebefore="24pt"
textalign="center"
useperiodafterappendixletter="yes"
></contentsLayout
><abstractLayout
font-size="14pt"
font-weight="bold"
spaceafter="12pt"
spacebefore="24pt"
textalign="center"
></abstractLayout
><acknowledgementsLayout
font-size="14pt"
font-weight="bold"
spaceafter="12pt"
spacebefore="24pt"
textalign="center"
></acknowledgementsLayout
><prefaceLayout
font-size="14pt"
font-weight="bold"
spaceafter="12pt"
spacebefore="24pt"
textalign="center"
></prefaceLayout
></frontMatterLayout
><bodyLayout
><comment
>Body Layout</comment
><section1Layout
><sectionTitleLayout
font-size="14pt"
font-weight="bold"
spaceafter="12pt"
spacebefore="24pt"
textalign="center"
></sectionTitleLayout
></section1Layout
><section2Layout
><sectionTitleLayout
font-size="12pt"
font-weight="bold"
spaceafter="12pt"
spacebefore="12pt"
textalign="start"
></sectionTitleLayout
></section2Layout
><section3Layout
><sectionTitleLayout
font-style="italic"
font-weight="bold"
spaceafter="12pt"
spacebefore="12pt"
textalign="start"
></sectionTitleLayout
></section3Layout
><section4Layout
><sectionTitleLayout
font-style="italic"
spaceafter="12pt"
spacebefore="12pt"
textalign="start"
></sectionTitleLayout
></section4Layout
><section5Layout
ignore="yes"
><sectionTitleLayout
></sectionTitleLayout
></section5Layout
><section6Layout
ignore="yes"
><sectionTitleLayout
></sectionTitleLayout
></section6Layout
></bodyLayout
><backMatterLayout
><comment
>Back Matter Layout</comment
><acknowledgementsLayout
font-size="14pt"
font-weight="bold"
spaceafter="12pt"
spacebefore="24pt"
textalign="center"
></acknowledgementsLayout
><appendixLayout
><appendixTitleLayout
font-size="14pt"
font-weight="bold"
spaceafter="12pt"
spacebefore="24pt"
textafterletter=". "
textalign="center"
></appendixTitleLayout
></appendixLayout
><glossaryLayout
font-size="14pt"
font-weight="bold"
spaceafter="12pt"
spacebefore="24pt"
textalign="center"
></glossaryLayout
><referencesTitleLayout
font-size="14pt"
font-weight="bold"
spaceafter="12pt"
spacebefore="24pt"
textalign="center"
></referencesTitleLayout
><xi:include
href="../../asheninka/doc/SILInternationalReferencesStylesheet.xml"
xpointer="element(/1)"
xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
></xi:include
><indexLayout
font-size="14pt"
font-weight="bold"
spaceafter="12pt"
spacebefore="24pt"
textalign="center"
></indexLayout
></backMatterLayout
><contentLayout
><comment
>Document Content Layout</comment
><exampleLayout
indent-after=".125in"
indent-before=".125in"
></exampleLayout
><interlinearSourceStyle
></interlinearSourceStyle
><endnoteRefLayout
></endnoteRefLayout
><figureLayout
captionLocation="after"
><figureLabelLayout
textafter=" "
></figureLabelLayout
><figureNumberLayout
></figureNumberLayout
><figureCaptionLayout
textbefore=" "
></figureCaptionLayout
></figureLayout
><figureRefLayout
></figureRefLayout
><tablenumberedLayout
captionLocation="after"
><tablenumberedLabelLayout
textafter=" "
></tablenumberedLabelLayout
><tablenumberedNumberLayout
></tablenumberedNumberLayout
><tablenumberedCaptionLayout
textbefore="  "
></tablenumberedCaptionLayout
></tablenumberedLayout
><tablenumberedRefLayout
></tablenumberedRefLayout
></contentLayout
></publisherStyleSheet
></styledPaper
></xlingpaper
>
